<?hard-pagebreak?>
<section><title>practice: packet forwarding</title>
	<para>0. You have the option to select (or create) an internal network when adding a network card in VirtualBox or VMWare. Use this option to create two internal networks. I named them <command>leftnet</command> and <command>rightnet</command>, but you can choose any other name.</para>
	<para><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/LAN_networks.png" format="EPS" align="center"></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject></para>
	<para>1. Set up two Linux machines, one on <command>leftnet</command>, the other on <command>rightnet</command>. Make sure they both get an ip-address in the correct subnet. These two machines will be 'left' and 'right' from the 'router'.</para>
	<para><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/leftnet_rightnet_router2.png" format="EPS" align="center"></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject></para>
	<para>2. Set up a third Linux computer with three network cards, one on <command>leftnet</command>, the other on <command>rightnet</command>. This computer will be the 'router'. Complete the table below with the relevant names, ip-addresses and mac-addresses.</para>
<table frame='all'><title>Packet Forwarding Exercise</title>
<?dbfo table-width="100%" ?>
<tgroup cols='5' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
<colspec colname='c1' colwidth="1*" align="left"/>
<colspec colname='c2' colwidth="3*" align="left"/>
<colspec colname='c3' colwidth="3*" align="left"/>
<colspec colname='c4' colwidth="3*" align="left"/>
<colspec colname='c5' colwidth="3*" align="left"/>
<thead>
<row>
  <entry></entry>
  <entry>leftnet computer</entry>
  <entry namest="c2" nameend="c3">the router</entry>
  <entry>rightnet computer</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
  <entry>MAC</entry>
  <entry></entry>
  <entry></entry>
  <entry></entry>
  <entry></entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry>IP</entry>
  <entry></entry>
  <entry></entry>
  <entry></entry>
  <entry></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
	<para>3. How can you verify whether the <command>router</command> will allow packet forwarding by default or not ? Test that you can ping from the <command>router</command> to the two other machines, and from those two machines to the <command>router</command>. Use <command>arp -a</command> to make sure you are connected with the correct <command>mac addresses</command>.</para>
<?hard-pagebreak?>
	<para>4. Ping from the leftnet computer to the rightnet computer. Enable and/or disable packet forwarding on the <command>router</command> and verify what happens to the ping between the two networks. If you do not succeed in pinging between the two networks (on different subnets), then use a sniffer like wireshark or tcpdump to discover the problem.</para>
	<para>5. Use wireshark or tcpdump -xx to answer the following questions. Does the source MAC change when a packet passes through the filter ? And the destination MAC ? What about source and destination IP-addresses ?</para>
	<para>6. Remember the third network card on the router ? Connect this card to a LAN with internet connection. On many LAN's the command <command>dhclient eth0</command> just works (replace <command>eth0</command> with the correct interface).</para>
	<screen>root@router~# dhclient eth0</screen>
	<para>You now have a setup similar to this picture. What needs to be done to give internet access to <command>leftnet</command> and <command>rightnet</command>.</para>
	<para><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/leftnet_rightnet_router3.png" format="EPS" align="center"></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject></para>
</section>
