<section><title>network address translation</title>
<section><title>about NAT</title>
	<para>A NAT device is a router that is also changing the source and/or target ip-address in packets. It is typically used to connect multiple computers in a private address range with the (public) internet. A NAT can hide private addresses from the internet.</para>
	<para>NAT was developed to mitigate the use of real ip addresses, to allow private address ranges to reach the internet and back, and to not disclose details about internal networks to the outside.</para>
	<para>The nat table in iptables adds two new chains. PREROUTING allows altering of packets before they reach the INPUT chain. POSTROUTING allows altering packets after they exit the OUTPUT chain.</para>
	<para>Use <command>iptables -t nat -nvL</command> to look at the NAT table. The screenshot below shows an empty NAT table.</para>
	<screen>
[root@RHEL5 ~]# iptables -t nat -nL
Chain PREROUTING (policy ACCEPT)
target     prot opt source               destination         

Chain POSTROUTING (policy ACCEPT)
target     prot opt source               destination         

Chain OUTPUT (policy ACCEPT)
target     prot opt source               destination         
[root@RHEL5 ~]#
	</screen>
</section>
<section><title>SNAT (Source NAT)</title>
	<para>The goal of source nat is to change the source address inside a packet before it leaves the system (e.g. to the internet). The destination will return the packet to the NAT-device. This means our NAT-device will need to keep a table in memory of all the packets it changed, so it can deliver the packet to the original source (e.g. in the private network).</para>
	<para>Because SNAT is about packets leaving the system, it uses the POSTROUTING chain.</para>
	<para>Here is an example SNAT rule. The rule says that packets coming from 10.1.1.0/24 network and exiting via eth1 will get the source ip-address set to 11.12.13.14. (Note that this is a one line command!)</para>
	<screen>
iptables -t nat -A POSTROUTING -o eth1 -s 10.1.1.0/24 -j SNAT \
--to-source 11.12.13.14
	</screen>
	<para>Of course there must exist a proper iptables filter setup to allow the packet to traverse from one network to the other.</para>
</section>
<section><title>SNAT example setup</title>
	<para>This example script uses a typical nat setup. The internal (eth0) network has access via SNAT to external (eth1) webservers (port 80).</para>
	<screen>
#!/bin/bash
#
# iptables script for simple classic nat websurfing
# eth0 is internal network, eth1 is internet
#
echo 0 > /proc/sys/net/ipv4/ip_forward
iptables -P INPUT ACCEPT
iptables -P OUTPUT ACCEPT
iptables -P FORWARD DROP
iptables -A FORWARD -i eth0 -o eth1 -s 10.1.1.0/24 -p tcp \
--dport 80 -j ACCEPT
iptables -A FORWARD -i eth1 -o eth0 -d 10.1.1.0/24 -p tcp \
--sport 80 -j ACCEPT
iptables -t nat -A POSTROUTING -o eth1 -s 10.1.1.0/24 -j SNAT \
--to-source 11.12.13.14
echo 1 > /proc/sys/net/ipv4/ip_forward
</screen>
</section>
<section><title>IP masquerading</title>
	<para>IP masquerading is very similar to SNAT, but is meant for dynamic interfaces. Typical example are broadband 'router/modems' connected to the internet and receiving a different ip-address from the isp, each time they are cold-booted.</para>
	<para>The only change needed to convert the SNAT script to a masquerading is one line.</para>
	<screen>
iptables -t nat -A POSTROUTING -o eth1 -s 10.1.1.0/24 -j MASQUERADE
	</screen>
</section>
<section><title>DNAT (Destination NAT)</title>
	<para>DNAT is typically used to allow packets from the internet to be redirected to an internal server (in your DMZ) and in a private address range that is inaccessible directly form the internet.</para>
	<para>This example script allows internet users to reach your internal (192.168.1.99) server via ssh (port 22).</para>
	<screen>
#!/bin/bash
#
# iptables script for DNAT
# eth0 is internal network, eth1 is internet
#
echo 0 > /proc/sys/net/ipv4/ip_forward
iptables -P INPUT ACCEPT
iptables -P OUTPUT ACCEPT
iptables -P FORWARD DROP
iptables -A FORWARD -i eth0 -o eth1 -s 10.1.1.0/24 -j ACCEPT
iptables -A FORWARD -i eth1 -o eth0 -p tcp --dport 22 -j ACCEPT
iptables -t nat -A PREROUTING -i eth1 -p tcp --dport 22 \
-j DNAT --to-destination 192.168.1.99
echo 1 > /proc/sys/net/ipv4/ip_forward
</screen>
</section>
</section>
