	<section><title>Certification</title>
		<section><title>LPI: Linux Professional Institute</title>
			<section><title>LPIC Level 1</title>
				<para>This is the junior level certification. You need to pass exams 101 and 102 to achieve <command>LPIC 1 certification</command><indexterm><primary>LPIC 1 Certification</primary></indexterm>. To pass level one, you will need Linux command line, user management, backup and restore, installation, networking and basic system administration skills.</para>
			</section>
			<section><title>LPIC Level 2</title>
				<para>This is the advanced level certification. You need to be LPIC 1 certified and pass exams 201 and 202 to achieve <command>LPIC 2 certification</command><indexterm><primary>LPIC 2 Certification</primary></indexterm>. To pass level two, you will need to be able to administer medium sized Linux networks, including Samba, mail, news, proxy, firewall, web and ftp servers.</para>
			</section>
			<section><title>LPIC Level 3</title>
				<para>This is the senior level certification. It contains one core exam (301) which tests advanced skills mainly about ldap. To achieve this level you also need LPIC Level 2 and pass a specialty exam (302 or 303). Exam 302 mainly focuses on Samba, 303 is about advanced security. More info on http://www.lpi.org.</para>
			</section>
			<section><title>Ubuntu</title>
				<para>When you are LPIC Level 1 certified, you can take a LPI Ubuntu exam (199) and become Ubuntu certified.</para>
			</section>
		</section>
		<section><title>Red Hat Certified Engineer</title>
			<para>The big difference with most certs is that there are no multiple choice questions for <command>RHCE</command><indexterm><primary>RHCE</primary></indexterm>. Red Hat Certified Engineers have taken a live exam consisting of two parts. First they have to troubleshoot and maintain an existing but broken setup (scoring at least 80 percent), second they have to install and configure a machine (scoring at least 70 percent).</para>
		</section>
		<section><title>MySQL</title>
			<para>There are two tracks for MySQL certification; Certified MySQL 5.0 Developer (CMDEV) and Certified MySQL 5.0 DBA (CMDBA). The <command>CMDEV</command><indexterm><primary>CMDEV</primary></indexterm> is focused at database application developers, the <command>CMDBA</command><indexterm><primary>CMDBA</primary></indexterm> is for database administrators. Both tracks require two exams each. The MySQL cluster DBA certification requires CMDBA certification and passing the CMCDBA exam.</para>
		</section>
		<section><title>Novell CLP/CLE</title>
			<para>To become a <command>Novell Certified Linux Professional</command><indexterm><primary>Novell Certified Linux Professional</primary></indexterm>, you have to take a live practicum. This is a VNC session to a set of real SLES servers. You have to perform several tasks and are free to choose your method (commandline or YaST or ...). No multiple choice involved.</para>
		</section>
		<section><title>Sun Solaris</title>
			<para>Sun uses the classical formula of multiple choice exams for certification. Passing two exams for an operating system gets you the Solaris Certified Administrator for Solaris X title.</para>
		</section>
		<section><title>Other certifications</title>
			<para>There are many other less known certs like EC council's Certified Ethical Hacker, CompTIA's Linux+ and Sair's Linux GNU.</para>
		</section>
	</section>
