<?hard-pagebreak?>
<section><title>Linux history</title>
	<para>Modern operating systems all have their roots in 1969 when <command>Dennis Ritchie</command><indexterm><primary>Dennis Ritchie</primary></indexterm> and <command>Ken Thompson</command><indexterm><primary>Ken Thompson</primary></indexterm> developed the C language and the <command>Unix</command><indexterm><primary>Unix</primary></indexterm> operating system at AT&#038;T Bell Labs. They shared their source code (yes, there was open source back in the Seventies) with the rest of the world, including the hippies in Berkeley California. By 1975, when AT&#038;T started selling Unix commercially, about half of the source code was written by others. The hippies were not happy when a commercial company sold software that they had written; the resulting (legal) battle ended in there being two versions of <command>Unix</command> in the Seventies : the official AT&#038;T Unix, and the free <command>BSD</command><indexterm><primary>BSD</primary></indexterm> Unix.</para>
	<para>In the Eighties many companies started developing their own Unix: IBM<indexterm><primary>IBM</primary></indexterm> created AIX<indexterm><primary>AIX</primary></indexterm>, Sun<indexterm><primary>Sun</primary></indexterm> SunOS<indexterm><primary>SunOS</primary></indexterm> (later Solaris<indexterm><primary>Solaris</primary></indexterm>), HP<indexterm><primary>HP</primary></indexterm> HP-UX<indexterm><primary>HP-UX</primary></indexterm> and about a dozen other companies did the same. The result was a mess of Unix dialects where you had a dozen different ways to do the same thing. And here is the first real root of <command>Linux</command>, when <command>Richard Stallman</command><indexterm><primary>Richard Stallman</primary></indexterm> aimed to end this era of Unix separation and everybody re-inventing the wheel. Richard started the <command>GNU</command><indexterm><primary>GNU</primary></indexterm> project (GNU is Not Unix) to make an operating system that was freely available for everyone, and where everyone could work together (like in the Seventies). Many of the command line tools that you use today on <command>Linux</command> or Solaris are GNU tools.</para>
	<para>The Nineties started with <command>Linus Torvalds</command><indexterm><primary>Linus Torvalds</primary></indexterm>, a Swedish speaking Finnish student, buying a 386 computer and writing a brand new POSIX compliant kernel. He put the source code online, thinking it would never support anything but 386 hardware. Many people embraced the combination of this kernel with the GNU tools, and the rest, as they say, is history.</para>
	<para>Today more than 90 percent of supercomputers (including the complete top 10), more than half of all smartphones, many millions of desktop computers, around 70 percent of all web servers, a large chunk of tablet computers, and several appliances (dvd-players, washing machines, dsl modems, routers, ...) run <command>Linux</command>. It is by far the most common operating system in the world.</para>
	<para>Linux kernel version 3.2 was released in January 2012. Its source code grew by almost two hundred thousand lines thanks to contributions from over 4000 developers paid by about 200 commercial companies including Red Hat, Intel, Broadcom, Texas Instruments, IBM, Novell, Qualcomm, Samsung, Nokia, Oracle, Google and even Microsoft.</para>
	<screen>http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dennis_Ritchie
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Stallman
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linus_Torvalds
http://kernel.org
http://lwn.net/Articles/472852/
http://www.linuxfoundation.org/
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linux
http://www.levenez.com/unix/ (a huge Unix history poster)</screen>
</section>
