<section><title>run a program as another user</title>
	<section><title>about sudo</title>
		<para>The sudo program allows a user to start a program with the credentials of another user. Before this works, the system administrator has to set up the <command>/etc/sudoers</command><indexterm><primary>/etc/sudoers</primary></indexterm> file. This can be useful to delegate administrative tasks to another user (without giving the root password).</para>
		<para>The screenshot below shows the usage of <command>sudo</command><indexterm><primary>sudo</primary></indexterm>. User <command>paul</command> received the right to run <command>useradd</command> with the credentials of <command>root</command><indexterm><primary>root</primary></indexterm>. This allows <command>paul</command> to create new users on the system without becoming <command>root</command> and without knowing the <command>root password</command>.</para>
		<screen>
paul@laika:~$ useradd -m inge
useradd: unable to lock password file
paul@laika:~$ sudo useradd -m inge
[sudo] password for paul: 
paul@laika:~$
		</screen>
        </section>

	<section><title>setuid on sudo</title>
		<para>The <command>sudo</command> binary has the <command>setuid</command><indexterm><primary>setuid</primary></indexterm> bit set, so any user can run it with the effective userid of root.</para>
		<screen>
paul@laika:~$ ls -l `which sudo`
-rwsr-xr-x 2 root root 107872 2008-05-15 02:41 /usr/bin/sudo
paul@laika:~$ 
		</screen>
	</section>
	<section><title>visudo</title>
		<para>Check the man page of <command>visudo</command><indexterm><primary>visudo(1)</primary></indexterm> before playing with the /etc/sudoers file.</para>
		<para></para>
	</section>
	<section><title>sudo su</title>
		<para>On some linux systems like Ubuntu and Kubuntu, the <command>root</command> user does not have a password set. This means that it is not possible to login as <command>root</command> (extra security). To perform tasks as <command>root</command>, the first user is given all <command>sudo rights</command><indexterm><primary>sudo(1)</primary></indexterm> via the <command>/etc/sudoers</command><indexterm><primary>/etc/sudoers</primary></indexterm>. In fact all users that are members of the admin group can use sudo to run all commands as root.</para>
	<screen>
root@laika:~# grep admin /etc/sudoers 
# Members of the admin group may gain root privileges
%admin ALL=(ALL) ALL
	</screen>
	 <para>The end result of this is that the user can type <command>sudo su -</command><indexterm><primary>sudo su -</primary></indexterm> and become root without having to enter the root password. The sudo command does require you to enter your own password. Thus the password prompt in the screenshot below is for sudo, not for su. </para>
		<screen>
paul@laika:~$ sudo su -
Password:
root@laika:~#
		</screen>
	</section>
</section>
