<section><title>About Groups</title>
	<para>Users can be listed in groups. Groups allow you to set permissions on the group level instead of setting permissions for every individual users. Every Unix or Linux distribution will have a graphical tool to manage groups. Novice users are adviced to use this graphical tool. More experienced users can use commandline tools to manage users, but be careful: some distribution do not allow the mixed use of GUI and CLI tools to manage groups (YaST in Novell Suse). Senior administrators can edit the relevant files directly with vi or vigr.</para>
</section>
<section><title>groupadd</title>
	<para>Groups can be created with the <command>groupadd</command><indexterm><primary>groupadd(1)</primary></indexterm> command. The example below shows the creation of five (empty) groups.</para>
	<screen>
root@laika:~# groupadd tennis
root@laika:~# groupadd football
root@laika:~# groupadd snooker
root@laika:~# groupadd formula1
root@laika:~# groupadd salsa
	</screen>
</section>
<section><title>/etc/group</title>
	<para>Users can be a member of several groups. Group membership is defined by the <command>/etc/group</command><indexterm><primary>/etc/group</primary></indexterm> file. </para>
<screen>
root@laika:~# tail -5 /etc/group
tennis:x:1006:
football:x:1007:
snooker:x:1008:
formula1:x:1009:
salsa:x:1010:
root@laika:~# 
</screen>
	<para>Before the colon is the group's name. The second field is the group's (encrypted) password (can be empty). The third field is the group identification or <command>GID</command><indexterm><primary>GID</primary></indexterm>. The fourth field is the list of members, these groups have no members.</para>
</section>
<section><title>usermod</title>
	<para>Group membership can be modified with the useradd or <command>usermod</command><indexterm><primary>usermod</primary></indexterm> command.</para>
	<screen>
root@laika:~# usermod -a -G tennis Inge
root@laika:~# usermod -a -G tennis Katrien
root@laika:~# usermod -a -G salsa Katrien
root@laika:~# usermod -a -G snooker Sandra
root@laika:~# usermod -a -G formula1 Annelies
root@laika:~# tail -5 /etc/group
tennis:x:1006:Inge,Katrien
football:x:1007:
snooker:x:1008:Sandra
formula1:x:1009:Annelies
salsa:x:1010:Katrien
root@laika:~# 
	</screen>
	<para>Be careful when using usermod to add people to groups. The usermod command will by default <command>remove</command> users from the groups that are not listed in the command! Using the <command>-a</command> (append) switch prevents this behaviour.</para>
</section>
<section><title>groupmod</title>
	  <para>You can change the group name with the <command>groupmod</command><indexterm><primary>groupmod(1)</primary></indexterm> command.</para>
	<screen>
root@laika:~# groupmod -n darts snooker 
root@laika:~# tail -5 /etc/group
tennis:x:1006:Inge,Katrien
football:x:1007:
formula1:x:1009:Annelies
salsa:x:1010:Katrien
darts:x:1008:Sandra
	</screen>
</section>
<section><title>groups</title>
	<para>A user can type the <command>groups</command><indexterm><primary>groups(1)</primary></indexterm> command to see a list of groups where the user belongs to.</para>
	<screen>
[Harry@RHEL4b ~]$ groups
Harry sports
[Harry@RHEL4b ~]$ 
	</screen>
</section>
<section><title>gpasswd</title>
	<para>You can delegate control of group membership to another user with the <command>gpasswd</command><indexterm><primary>gpasswd</primary></indexterm> command. In the example below we delegate permissions to add and remove group members to the sports group to Serena. Then we su to Serena and add Harry to the sports group.</para>
	<screen>
[root@RHEL4b ~]# gpasswd -A Serena sports
[root@RHEL4b ~]# su - Serena
[Serena@RHEL4b ~]$ id Harry
uid=516(Harry) gid=520(Harry) groups=520(Harry)
[Serena@RHEL4b ~]$ gpasswd -a Harry sports
Adding user Harry to group sports
[Serena@RHEL4b ~]$ id Harry
uid=516(Harry) gid=520(Harry) groups=520(Harry),522(sports)
[Serena@RHEL4b ~]$ tail -1 /etc/group
sports:x:522:Serena,Venus,Harry
[Serena@RHEL4b ~]$
	</screen>
	<para>Group administrators do not need to be a member of the group. They can even remove themselves from the group, this does not influence their ability to add or remove members.</para>
	<screen>
[Serena@RHEL4b ~]$ gpasswd -d Serena sports
Removing user Serena from group sports
[Serena@RHEL4b ~]$ exit
	</screen>
	<para>Information about group administrators is kept in the <command>/etc/gshadow</command><indexterm><primary>/etc/gshadow</primary></indexterm> file.</para>
	<screen>
[root@RHEL4b ~]# tail -1 /etc/gshadow
sports:!:Serena:Venus,Harry
[root@RHEL4b ~]#
	</screen>
</section>
<section><title>vigr</title>
	<para>Similar to vipw, the <command>vigr</command><indexterm><primary>vigr(1)</primary></indexterm> must be used to manually edit the /etc/group file, since it will do proper locking of the file. Only experienced senior administrators should use vi or vigr to manage groups.</para>
</section>
<section><title>Practice: Groups</title>
		<para>1. Create the groups tennis, football and sports.</para>
		<para>2. In one command, make Venus a member of tennis and sports.</para>
		<para>3. Rename the football group to foot.</para>
		<para>4. Use vi to add Serena to the tennis group.</para>
		<para>5. Use the id command to verify that Serena is a member of tennis.</para>
		<para>6. Make someone responsible for managing group membership of foot and sports. Test that it works.</para>
</section>
