<?hard-pagebreak?>
<section><title>network layers</title>
	<section><title>seven OSI layers</title>
		<para>When talking about protocol layers, people usually mention the seven layers of the <command>osi</command> protocol (Application, Presentation, Session, Transport, Network, Data Link and Physical). We will discuss layers 2 and 3 in depth, and focus less on the other layers. The reason is that these layers are important for understanding networks. You will hear administrators use words like "this is a layer 2 device" or "this is a layer 3 broadcast", and you should be able to understand what they are talking about.</para>
	</section>
	<section><title>four DoD layers</title>
		<para>The <command>DoD</command> (or tcp/ip) model has only four layers, roughly mapping its <command>network access layer</command> to OSI layers 1 and 2 (Physical and Datalink), its <command>internet</command> (IP) layer to the OSI <command>network layer</command>, its <command>host-to-host</command> (tcp, udp) layer to OSI layer 4 (transport) and its <command>application layer</command> to OSI layers 5, 6 and 7.</para>
		<para>Below an attempt to put OSI and DoD layers next to some protocols and devices.</para>
 		<mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/networklayers.png" format="EPS" align="center"></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject>
	</section>
	<section><title>short introduction to the physical layer</title>
		<para>The physical layer, or <command>layer 1</command>, is all about voltage, electrical signals and mechanical connections. Some networks might still use <command>coax</command> cables, but most will have migrated to <command>utp</command> (cat 5 or better) with <command>rj45</command> connectors.</para>
		<para>Devices like <command>repeaters</command> and <command>hubs</command> are part of this layer. You cannot use software to 'see' a <command>repeater</command> or <command>hub</command> on the network. The only thing these devices are doing is amplifying electrical signals on cables. <command>Passive hubs</command> are multiport amplifiers that amplify an incoming electrical signal on all other connections. <command>Active hubs</command> do this by reading and retransmitting bits, without interpreting any meaning in those bits.</para>
		<para>Network technologies like <command>csma/cd</command> and <command>token ring</command> are defined on this layer.</para>
		<para>This is all we have to say about <command>layer 1</command> in this book.</para>
	</section>
	<section><title>short introduction to the data link layer</title>
		<para>The data link layer, or <command>layer 2</command> is about frames. A frame has a <command>crc</command> (cyclic redundancy check). In the case of ethernet (802.3), each network card is identifiable by a unique 48-bit <command>mac</command> address (media access control address).</para>
		<para>On this layer we find devices like bridges and switches. A bridge is more intelligent than a hub because a <command>bridge</command> can make decisions based on the mac address of computers. A <command>switch</command> also understands mac addresses.</para>
		<para>In this book we will discuss commands like <command>arp</command> and <command>ifconfig</command> to explore this layer.</para>
	</section>
	<section><title>short introduction to the network layer</title>
		<para><command>Layer 3</command> is about ip packets. This layer gives every host a unique 32-bit ip address. But <command>ip</command> is not the only protocol on this layer, there is also icmp, igmp, ipv6 and more. A complete list can be found in the <command>/etc/protocols</command> file.</para>
		<para>On this layer we find devices like <command>routers</command> and layer 3 switches, devices that know (and have) an ip address.</para>
		<para>In tcp/ip this layer is commonly referred to as the <command>internet layer</command>.</para>
	</section>
	<section><title>short introduction to the transport layer</title>
		<para>We will discuss the <command>tcp</command> and <command>udp</command> protocols in the context of layer 4. The DoD model calls this the host-to-host layer.</para>
	</section>
	<section><title>layers 5, 6 and 7 </title>
		<para>The tcp/ip application layer includes layers 5, 6 and 7. Details on the difference between these layers are out of scope of this course.</para>
	</section>
	<section><title>network layers in this book</title>
		<para>Stacking of layers in this book is based on the <command>Protocols in Frame</command> explanation in the <command>wireshark</command> sniffer. When sniffing a dhcp packet, we notice the following in the sniffer.</para>
		<screen>[Protocols in Frame: eth:ip:udp:bootp]</screen>
		<para>Sniffing for ntp (Network Time Protocol) packets gives us this line, which makes us conclude to put <command>ntp</command> next to <command>bootp</command> in the protocol chart below.</para>
		<screen>[Protocols in Frame: eth:ip:udp:ntp]</screen>
		<para>Sniffing an <command>arp</command> broadcast makes us put arp next to <command>ip</command>. All these protocols are explained later in this chapter.</para>
		<screen>[Protocols in Frame: eth:arp]</screen>
		<para>Below is a protocol chart based on wireshark's knowledge. It contains some very common protocols that are discussed in this book. The chart does not contain all protocols.</para>
		<mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/networkprotocols.png" format="EPS" align="center"></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject>
	</section>
</section>
<?hard-pagebreak?>
<section><title>unicast, multicast, broadcast, anycast</title>
	<section><title>unicast</title>
		<para>A <command>unicast</command> communication originates from one computer and is destined for exactly one other computer (or host). It is common for computers to have many <command>unicast</command> communications.</para>
		<mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/unicast.png" format="EPS" align="center"></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject>
	</section>
	<section><title>multicast</title>
	<para>A <command>multicast</command><indexterm><primary>multicast</primary></indexterm> is destined for a group (of computers).</para>
		<mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/multicast.png" format="EPS" align="center"></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject>
		<para>Some examples of <command>multicast</command> are Realplayer (.sdp files) and <command>ripv2</command> (a routing protocol).</para>
	</section>
<?hard-pagebreak?>
	<section><title>broadcast</title>
		<para>A <command>broadcast</command><indexterm><primary>broadcast</primary></indexterm> is meant for everyone.</para>
		<mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/broadcast.png" format="EPS" align="center"></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject>
		<para>Typical example here is the BBC (British Broadcasting Corporation) broadcasting to everyone. In datacommunications a broadcast is most common confined to the <command>lan</command>.</para>
		<para>Careful, a <command>layer 2 broadcast</command> is very different from a <command>layer 3 broadcast</command>. A layer two broadcast is received by all network cards on the same segment (it does not pass any router), whereas a layer 3 broadcast is received by all hosts in the same ip subnet.</para>

	</section>
	<section><title>anycast</title>
		<para>The <command>root name servers</command><indexterm><primary>root servers(DNS)</primary></indexterm> of the internet use <command>anycast</command><indexterm><primary>anycast</primary></indexterm>. An <command>anycast</command> signal goes the the (geographically) nearest of a well defined group.</para>
		<mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/anycast.png" format="EPS" align="center"></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject>
	</section>
	<para>With thanks to the nice anonymous wikipedia contributor to put these pictures in the public domain.</para>
</section>
<?hard-pagebreak?>
<section><title>lan-wan-man</title>
	<para>The term <command>lan</command> is used for local area networks, as opposed to a <command>wan</command> for wide area networks. The difference between the two is determined by the <command>distance</command> between the computers, and not by the number of computers in a network. Some protocols like <command>atm</command> are designed for use in a <command>wan</command>, others like <command>ethernet</command> are designed for use in a <command>lan</command>.</para>
	<section><title>lan</title>
		<para>A <command>lan </command><indexterm><primary>LAN</primary></indexterm> (Local Area Network) is a local network. This can be one room, or one floor, or even one big building. We say <command>lan</command> as long as computers are <command>close</command> to each other. You can also define a <command>lan</command> when all computers are <command>ethernet</command> connected.</para>
		<para>A <command>lan</command> can contain multiple smaller <command>lan</command>'s. The picture below shows three <command>lan</command>'s that together make up one <command>lan</command>.</para>
	<mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/LAN_en.jpg" format="EPS" align="center"></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject>
	</section>
	<section><title>wan</title>
		<para>A <command>wan</command><indexterm><primary>WAN</primary></indexterm> (Wide Area Network) is a network with a lot of distance between the computers (or hosts). These hosts are often connected by <command>leased lines</command>. A <command>wan</command> does not use <command>ethernet</command>, but protocols like <command>fddi</command><indexterm><primary>fddi</primary></indexterm>, <command>frame relay</command><indexterm><primary>frame relay</primary></indexterm>, <command>ATM</command><indexterm><primary>atm</primary></indexterm> or <command>X.25</command><indexterm><primary>X.25</primary></indexterm> to connect computers (and networks).</para>
		<para>The picture below shows a branch office that is connected through <command>Frame Relay</command> with headquarters.</para>
	<mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/WAN.png" format="EPS" align="center"></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject>
		<para>The acronym <command>wan</command> is also used for large surface area networks like the <command>internet</command>.</para>
		<para><command>Cisco</command><indexterm><primary>Cisco</primary></indexterm> is known for their <command>wan</command> technology. They make <command>routers</command><indexterm><primary>router</primary></indexterm> that connect many <command>lan</command> networks using <command>wan</command> protocols.</para>
	</section>
	<section><title>man</title>
		<para>A <command>man</command><indexterm><primary>MAN</primary></indexterm> (Metropolitan Area Network) is something inbetween a <command>lan</command> and a <command>wan</command>, often comprising several buildings on the same campus or in the same city. A <command>man</command> can use <command>fddi</command> or <command>ethernet</command> or other protocols for connectivity.</para>
	</section>
	<section><title>pan-wpan</title>
		<para>Your home network is called a <command>pan</command><indexterm><primary>PAN</primary></indexterm> (Personal Area Network). A wireless <command>pan</command> is a <command>wpan</command><indexterm><primary>WPAN</primary></indexterm>.</para>
	</section>
</section>
<section><title>internet - intranet - extranet</title>
	<para>The <command>internet</command> is a global network. It connects many networks using the <command>tcp/ip</command> protocol stack.</para>
	<para>The origin of the <command>internet</command> is the <command>arpanet</command>. The <command>arpanet</command> was created in 1969, that year only four computers were connected in the network. In 1971 the first <command>e-mail</command> was sent over the <command>arpanet</command>. <command>E-mail</command> took 75 percent of all <command>arpanet</command> traffic in 1973. 1973 was also the year <command>ftp</command> was introduced, and saw the connection of the first European countries (Norway and UK). In 2009 the internet was available to 25 percent of the world population. In 2011 it is estimated that only a quarter of internet webpages are in English.</para>
	<para>An <command>intranet</command> is a private <command>tcp/ip</command> network. An <command>intranet</command> uses the same protocols as the <command>internet</command>, but is only accessible to people from within one organization.</para>
	<para>An <command>extranet</command> is similar to an <command>intranet</command>, but some trusted organizations (partners/clients/suppliers/...) also get access.</para>
</section>
<?hard-pagebreak?>
<section><title>tcp/ip</title>
	<section><title>history of tcp/ip</title>
		<para>In the Sixties development of the <command>tcp/ip</command> protocol stack was started by the US Department of Defense. In the Eighties a lot of commercial enterprises developed their own protocol stack: IBM created <command>sna</command>, Novell had <command>ipx/spx</command>, Microsoft completed <command>netbeui</command> and Apple worked with <command>appletalk</command>. All the efforts from the Eighties failed to survive the Nineties. By the end of the Nineties, almost all computers in the world were able to speak tcp/ip.</para>
		<para>In my humble opinion, the main reason for the survival of <command>tcp/ip</command> over all the other protocols is its openness. Everyone is free to develop and use the tcp/ip protocol suite.</para>
	</section>
	<section><title>rfc (request for comment)</title>
		<para>The protocols that are used on the internet are defined in <command>rfc's</command>. An rfc or <command>request for comment</command> describes the inner working of all internet protocols. The <command>IETF</command> (Internet Engineering Task Force) is the sole publisher of these protocols since 1986.</para>
		<para>The official website for the rfc's is <command>http://www.rfc-editor.org</command>. This website contains all rfc's in plain text, for example rfc2132 (which defines dhcp and bootp) is accessible at http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2132.txt.</para>
	</section>
	<para><command>tcp/ip</command> and how it works on Linux will be discussed in detail in the next chapter.</para>
</section>
<?hard-pagebreak?>
<section><title>topologie van een netwerk</title>
	<para>Meer info en mooie tekeningen op Wikipedia:</para>
	<screen>http://nl.wikipedia.org/wiki/Netwerktopologie
http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Network_topology</screen>
	<section><title>punt tot punt</title>
		<para>De eenvoudigste topologie van een netwerk is een <command>point-to-point</command><indexterm><primary>point-to-point</primary></indexterm> verbinding tussen twee toestellen. Bijvoorbeeld een telefoonverbinding op het oude telefoonnetwerk (<command>circuit switched</command><indexterm><primary>circuit switched</primary></indexterm>). Deze verbinding is meestal dynamisch, maar kan ook permanent zijn, zoals de rode telefoon.</para>
		<para>We spreken ook van een <command>punt-tot-punt</command><indexterm><primary>punt-tot-punt</primary></indexterm> verbinding als je twee computers verbindt met een <command>seriële</command><indexterm><primary>seriële verbinding</primary></indexterm> of een <command>parallelle</command><indexterm><primary>parallelle verbinding</primary></indexterm> kabel, of als je de netwerkkaarten rechtstreeks verbindt. Ook een klassieke <command>modem</command> verbinding tussen twee computers is een <command>punt-tot-punt</command> verbinding.</para>
		<para>Niet te verwarren met <command>peer-to-peer</command> waar een applicatie zorgt voor overzicht tussen de <command>peers</command>.</para>
	</section>
	<section><title>bus</title>
		<para>In een <command>bus</command><indexterm><primary>bus(netwerk)</primary></indexterm> netwerk is elke computer verbonden met dezelfde kabel (meestal een coax kabel). Aan de twee eindes van de <command>bus</command> zit dan een <command>terminator</command>. Met <command>T-stukjes</command><indexterm><primary>T-stuk(coax)</primary></indexterm> kan je dan computers bij op de kabel plaatsen. Er kan slechts één computer tegelijk gebruik maken van de <command>bus</command>. Als twee computers tegelijk zenden, dan botsen de signalen tegen elkaar. Deze botsing heet een <command>collision</command><indexterm><primary>collision</primary></indexterm>.</para>
	</section>
	<section><title>ster</title>
		<para>Van zodra we een centraal toestel hebben zoals een <command>hub</command><indexterm><primary>hub</primary></indexterm>, <command>switch</command><indexterm><primary>switch</primary></indexterm> of <command>MAU</command><indexterm><primary>mau</primary></indexterm> spreken we van een <command>ster</command><indexterm><primary>ster(netwerk)</primary></indexterm> netwerk. Elke computer heeft een eigen kabel naar dit centrale toestel.</para>
		<para>In theorie kan je de <command>point-to-point</command> topologie beschouwen als een ster met één arm.</para>
	</section>
	<section><title>ring</title>
		<para>Een <command>ring</command><indexterm><primary>ring(netwerk)</primary></indexterm> topologie bestaat uit toestellen die elk met twee andere toestellen verbonden zijn, en wel zo dat ze een ring vormen. Gegevens gaan van de ene <command>node</command> naar de volgende, en zo de hele ring rond. Een probleem met één verbinding kan de hele ring platleggen.</para>
		<para>Typisch voorbeeld hier is een <command>Token Ring</command><indexterm><primary>Token Ring</primary></indexterm> netwerk. Deze technologie van IBM bestond fysisch uit een <command>ster</command> topologie met centrale <command>MAU</command><indexterm><primary>MultiStation Access Unit</primary></indexterm> (Multistation Access Unit) en speciale <command>token ring</command> kabels naar elke computer. Logisch gezien vormden de computers een ring. Telkens was er één computer die het <command>token</command><indexterm><primary>token</primary></indexterm> had, deze computer kon zenden op de <command>ring</command>.</para>
	</section>
	<section><title>tree</title>
		<para>Een netwerk kan ook hierarchisch georganiseerd zijn, zoals een boomstructuur. We spreken dan van een <command>tree</command><indexterm><primary>tree(netwerk)</primary></indexterm> met een <command>root node</command> aan de top van de boomstructuur. Type voorbeeld is de logische structuur van <command>DNS</command> servers op internet.</para>
	</section>
	<section><title>mesh</title>
		<para>Elke computer in een <command>mesh</command> kan met vele (of alle) andere computers verbonden zijn.</para>
		<para>Een <command>mesh</command><indexterm><primary>mesh</primary></indexterm> netwerk bestaat dus uit computers die allen dienst kunnen doen als <command>router</command><indexterm><primary>router</primary></indexterm>.</para>
	</section>
	<section><title>hybride</title>
		<para>Elke combinatie van bovenstaande architecturen die niet onder één van deze valt, noemt men een <command>hybride</command><indexterm><primary>hybride netwerk</primary></indexterm> netwerk.</para>
	</section>
</section>
<?hard-pagebreak?>
<section><title>toestellen en lagen</title>
<para>In een netwerk vinden we heel wat toestellen (devices). We zetten ze even laag per laag op een rijtje. </para>
	<section><title>physical</title>
		<para>Toestellen in laag 1 zijn in principe onzichtbaar op ons netwerk. We kunnen ze niet allemaal eenvoudig met software detecteren. We vinden hier onder andere de <command>netwerkkaart</command><indexterm><primary>netwerkkaart</primary></indexterm>, de <command>repeater</command><indexterm><primary>repeater</primary></indexterm>, de <command>hub</command><indexterm><primary>hub</primary></indexterm> en de <command>modem</command><indexterm><primary>modem</primary></indexterm>.</para>
		<para>Hieronder de voorstelling van een <command>hub</command> in een netwerkdiagram.</para>
 		<mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/hub_logo.png" format="EPS" align="center"></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject>
		<para>De <command>netwerkkaart</command> of <command>nic (Network Interface Card)</command><indexterm><primary>nic</primary></indexterm> of ook <command>network adapter</command><indexterm><primary>network adapter</primary></indexterm> is tegenwoordig een vast onderdeel van elke computer. De netwerkkaart ontvangt elektrische signalen en zet deze om in bytes (en omgekeerd). De netwerkkaart controleert ook of een packetje van het netwerk wel voor haar is of niet. Indien niet, dan gooit de netwerkkaart dit packetje weg (<command>drop</command><indexterm><primary>drop</primary></indexterm>).</para>
		<para>De meeste netwerkkaarten vandaag zijn <command>ethernet</command><indexterm><primary>ethernet</primary></indexterm> kaarten met een 48-bit uniek <command>mac-adres</command><indexterm><primary>mac</primary></indexterm>. Enkele jaren terug waren ook <command>Token Ring</command><indexterm><primary>Token Ring</primary></indexterm> kaarten courant in gebruik.</para>
		<para>Een <command>repeater</command><indexterm><primary>repeater</primary></indexterm> is een versterker. Elektrische signalen verzwakken, dus als de netwerkkabel te lang is, dan kan een repeater het signaal versterken.</para>
		<para>Een <command>hub</command><indexterm><primary>hub</primary></indexterm> wordt ook wel een <command>multiport repeater</command><indexterm><primary>multiport repeater</primary></indexterm> genoemd. Net zoals een <command>repeater</command> zal ook een hub het elektrische signaal versterken. Daar waar een repeater tussen twee kabels zit, zit een hub tussen meerdere kabels, en versterkt hij het signaal naar alle verbonden kabels.</para>
		<para>Hubs kunnen <command>actief</command> of <command>passief</command> zijn. Een passieve hub versterkt het elektrische signaal, en logischerwijs ook de ruis op het kanaal. Te veel passieve hubs achter elkaar zorgt voor een te grote versterking van de ruis, waardoor het signaal verloren kan gaan.</para>
		<para>Een <command>actieve hub</command><indexterm><primary>hub (actief)</primary></indexterm> is slimmer dan een <command>passieve hub</command><indexterm><primary>hub (passief)</primary></indexterm>. In plaats van het signaal gewoon te versterken, leest een actieve hub de bits van een signaal, en stuurt deze bits naar alle verbonden kanalen. Op deze manier treedt er geen ruisversterking op.</para>
		<para>Een <command>modem</command><indexterm><primary>modem</primary></indexterm> (<command>modulator/demodulator</command><indexterm><primary>moduleren</primary></indexterm>) is een toestel dat (in het geval van een <command>pots-modem</command>) bits omzet in geluid, en omgekeerd aan de andere kant van de lijn dit geluid weer omzet in dezelfde bits.</para>
		<para>Een <command>kabel modem</command> zoals die van Telenet of Brutele vertaalt bits naar frequenties die oorspronkelijk bedoeld waren om TV-signalen door te sturen. Ook <command>ADSL</command><indexterm><primary>adsl</primary></indexterm> modems gebruiken een frequentie die buiten de menselijke stem liggen.</para>
	</section>
	<section><title>data link</title>
		<para>In deze laag vinden we toestellen zoals een <command>bridge</command><indexterm><primary>bridge</primary></indexterm> en een <command>switch</command><indexterm><primary>switch</primary></indexterm>. In dat laatste geval uiteraard een <command>layer 2 switch</command>.</para>
		<para>Hieronder de voorstelling van een <command>switch</command> in een netwerkdiagram.</para>
 		<mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/switch_logo.png" format="EPS" align="center"></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject>
		<para>Een <command>bridge</command> en <command>switch</command> zijn beide slimmer dan een hub of repeater, in de zin dat deze laatste niet weten wat een mac-adres is. Een bridge en een switch interpreteren het mac-adres om te weten of (in het geval van de bridge) en waar (in het geval van de switch) ze het packetje doorsturen.</para>
		<para>Een echte bridge is zeldzaam vandaag (want een switch kan alles wat een bridge kan).</para>
	</section>
	<section><title>network</title>
		<para>De <command>router</command><indexterm><primary>router</primary></indexterm> en de <command>layer 3 switch</command><indexterm><primary>layer 3 switch</primary></indexterm> zijn typische layer 3 toestellen. Toestellen in deze laag weten wat een ip-adres is, en kunnen uiteraard ook alles wat <command>layer 2 devices</command> kunnen.</para>
		<para>Hieronder de voorstelling van een <command>router</command> in een netwerkdiagram.</para>
 		<mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/router_logo.png" format="EPS" align="center"></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject>
		<para>Een echte router verbindt netwerken (bijvoorbeeld ethernet met T1, of ADSL met WiFi), maar de term wordt ook gebruikt voor ethernet-ethernet toestellen.</para>
		<para>Een layer 3 switch kent bijvoorbeeld <command>icmp</command><indexterm><primary>icmp</primary></indexterm> en wordt ook gebruikt om sniffen van het netwerk te verhinderen.</para>
	</section>
	<section><title>hogere lagen</title>
		<para>Een <command>gateway</command><indexterm><primary>gateway</primary></indexterm> is een toestel dat protocols vertaalt, bijvoorbeeld <command>NetBIOS</command> naar <command>tcp/ip</command>.</para>
	</section>
</section>
