<section><title>About Domain Controllers</title>
	<section><title>Windows NT4</title>
		<para>Windows NT4 works with single master replication domain controllers. There is exactly one PDC (Primary Domain Controller) in the domain, and zero or more BDC's (Backup Domain Controllers). Samba 3 has all features found in Windows NT4 PDC and BDC, and more. This includes file and print serving, domain control with single logon, logon scripts, home directories and roaming profiles.</para>
	</section>
	<section><title>Windows 200x</title>
		<para>With Windows 2000 came Active Directory. AD includes multimaster replication and group policies. Samba 3 can only be a member server in Active Directory, it cannot manage group policies. Samba 4 can do this (in beta).</para>
	</section>
	<section><title>Samba 3</title>
		<para>Samba 3 can act as a domain controller in its own domain. In a Windows NT4 domain, with one Windows NT4 PDC and zero or more BDC's, Samba 3 can only be a member server. The same is valid for Samba 3 in an Active Directory Domain. In short, a Samba 3 domain controller can not share domain control with Windows domain controllers.</para>
	</section>
	<section><title>Samba 4</title>
		<para>Samba 4 can be a domain controller in an Active Directory domain, including managing group policies. As of this writing, Samba 4 is not released for production!</para>
	</section>
</section>
<section><title>About security modes</title>
	<section><title>security = share</title>
		<para>The 'Windows for Workgroups' way of working, a client requests connection to a share and provides a password for that connection. Aanyone who knows a password for a share can access that share. This security model was common in Windows 3.11, Windows 95, Windows 98 and Windows ME.</para>
	</section>
	<section><title>security = user</title>
		<para>The client will send a userid + password before the server knows which share the client wants to access. This mode should be used whenever the samba server is in control of the user database. Both for standalone and samba domain controllers.</para>
	</section>
	<section><title>security = domain</title>
		<para>This mode will allow samba to verify user credentials using NTLM in Windows NT4 and in all Active Directory domains. This is similar to Windows NT4 BDC's joining a native Windows 2000/3 Active Directory domain.</para>
	</section>
	<section><title>security = ads</title>
		<para>This mode will make samba use Kerberos to connect to the Active Directory domain.</para>
	</section>
	<section><title>security = server</title>
		<para>This mode is obsolete, it can be used to forward authentication to another server.</para>
	</section>
</section>
<section><title>About password backends</title>
	<para>The previous chapters all used the <command>smbpasswd</command><indexterm><primary>/etc/samba/smbpasswd</primary></indexterm> user database. For domain control we opt for the <command>tdbsam</command><indexterm><primary>tdbsam</primary></indexterm> password backend. Another option would be to use LDAP. Larger domains will benefit from using LDAP instead of the not so scalable tdbsam. When you need more than one Domain Controller, then the Samba team advises to not use tdbsam.</para>
</section>
<section><title>[global] section in smb.conf</title>
	<para>Now is a good time to start adding comments in your smb.conf. First we will take a look at the naming of our domain and server in the <command>[global]</command> section, and at the domain controlling parameters.</para>
	<section><title>security</title>
		<para>The security must be set to user (which is the default). This mode will make samba control the user accounts, so it will allow samba to act as a domain controller.</para>
		<screen>security = user</screen>
	</section>
	<section><title>os level</title>
		<para>A samba server is the most stable computer in the network, so it should win all browser elections (<command>os level</command> above 32) to become the <command>browser master</command><indexterm><primary>browser master</primary></indexterm></para>
		<screen>os level = 33</screen>
	</section>
	<section><title>passdb backend</title>
		<para>The <command>passdb backend</command> parameter will determine whether samba uses <command>smbpasswd</command>, <command>tdbsam</command> or ldap.</para>
		<screen>passdb backend = tdbsam</screen>
	</section>
	<section><title>preferred master</title>
		<para>Setting the <command>preferred master</command> parameter to yes will make the nmbd daemon force an election on startup.</para>
		<screen>preferred master = yes</screen>
	</section>
	<section><title>domain logons</title>
		<para>Setting the <command>domain logons</command> parameter will make this samba server a domain controller.</para>
		<screen>domain logons = yes</screen>
	</section>
	<section><title>domain master</title>
		<para>Setting the <command>domain master</command> parameter can cause samba to claim the <command>domain master browser</command> role for its workgroup. Don't use this parameter in a workgroup with an active NT4 PDC.</para>
		<screen>domain master = yes</screen>
	</section>
	<section><title>[global] section</title>
		<para>The screenshot below shows a sample [global] section for a samba domain controller.</para>
		<screen>
[global]
# names
	workgroup = SPORTS
	netbios name = DCSPORTS
	server string = Sports Domain Controller
# domain control parameters
	security = user
	os level = 33
	preferred master = Yes
	domain master = Yes
	domain logons = Yes
		</screen>
	</section>
</section>
<section><title>netlogon share</title>
	<para>Part of the microsoft definition for a domain controller is that it should have a <command>netlogon share</command>. This is the relevant part of smb.conf to create this netlogon share on Samba.</para>
	<screen>
[netlogon]
comment = Network Logon Service
path = /srv/samba/netlogon
admin users = root
guest ok = Yes
browseable = No
	</screen>
</section>
<section><title>other [share] sections</title>
	<para>We create some sections for file shares, to test the samba server. Users can all access the general sports file share, but only group members can access their own sports share.</para>
	<screen>
[sports]
comment = Information about all sports
path = /srv/samba/sports
valid users = @ntsports
read only = No

[tennis]
comment = Information about tennis
path = /srv/samba/tennis
valid users = @nttennis
read only = No

[football]
comment = Information about football
path = /srv/samba/football
valid users = @ntfootball
read only = No
	</screen>
</section>
<section><title>Users and Groups</title>
	<para>To be able to use users and groups in the samba domain controller, we can first set up some groups on the Linux computer.</para>
	<screen>
[root@RHEL52 samba]# groupadd ntadmins
[root@RHEL52 samba]# groupadd ntsports
[root@RHEL52 samba]# groupadd ntfootball
[root@RHEL52 samba]# groupadd nttennis
	</screen>
	<para>This enables us to add group membership info to some new users for our samba domain. Don't forget to give them a password.</para>
	<para></para>
	<screen>
[root@RHEL52 samba]# useradd -m -G ntadmins Administrator
[root@RHEL52 samba]# useradd -m -G ntsports,nttennis venus
[root@RHEL52 samba]# useradd -m -G ntsports,nttennis kim
[root@RHEL52 samba]# useradd -m -G ntsports,nttennis jelena
[root@RHEL52 samba]# useradd -m -G ntsports,ntfootball figo
[root@RHEL52 samba]# useradd -m -G ntsports,ntfootball ronaldo
[root@RHEL52 samba]# useradd -m -G ntsports,ntfootball pfaff
	</screen>
	<para>It is always safe to verify creation of users, groups and passwords in /etc/passwd, /etc/shadow and /etc/group.</para>
	<screen>
[root@RHEL52 samba]# tail -11 /etc/group
ntadmins:x:507:Administrator
ntsports:x:508:venus,kim,jelena,figo,ronaldo,pfaff
ntfootball:x:509:figo,ronaldo,pfaff
nttennis:x:510:venus,kim,jelena
Administrator:x:511:
venus:x:512:
kim:x:513:
jelena:x:514:
figo:x:515:
ronaldo:x:516:
pfaff:x:517:
	</screen>
</section>
<section><title>tdbsam</title>
	<para>Next we must make these users known to samba with the smbpasswd tool. When you add the first user to <command>tdbsam</command><indexterm><primary>tdbsam</primary></indexterm>, the file <command>/etc/samba/passdb.tdb</command><indexterm><primary>/etc/samba/passdb.tdb</primary></indexterm> will be created.</para>
	<screen>
[root@RHEL52 samba]# smbpasswd -a root
New SMB password:
Retype new SMB password:
tdbsam_open: Converting version 0 database to version 3.
Added user root.
	</screen>
	<para>Adding all the other users generates less output, because tdbsam is already created.</para>
	<screen>
[root@RHEL4b samba]# smbpasswd -a root
New SMB password:
Retype new SMB password:
Added user root.
	</screen>
</section>
<section><title>about computer accounts</title>
	<para>Every NT computer (Windows NT, 2000, XP, Vista) can become a member of a domain. Joining the domain (by right-clicking on My Computer) means that a computer account will be created in the domain. This computer account also has a password (but you cannot know it) to prevent other computers with the same name from accidentally becoming member of the domain. The computer account created by Samba is visible in the <command>/etc/passwd</command><indexterm><primary>/etc/passwd</primary></indexterm> file on Linux. Computer accounts appear as a normal user account, but end their name with a dollar sign. Below a screenshot of the windows 2003 computer account, created by Samba 3.</para>
	<screen>
[root@RHEL52 samba]# tail -5 /etc/passwd
jelena:x:510:514::/home/jelena:/bin/bash
figo:x:511:515::/home/figo:/bin/bash
ronaldo:x:512:516::/home/ronaldo:/bin/bash
pfaff:x:513:517::/home/pfaff:/bin/bash
w2003ee$:x:514:518::/home/nobody:/bin/false
	</screen>
	<para>To be able to create the account, you will need to provide credentials of an account with the permission to create accounts (by default only root can do this on Linux). And we will have to tell Samba how to to this, by adding an <command>add machine script</command> to the global section of smb.conf.</para>
	<screen>
add machine script = /usr/sbin/useradd -s /bin/false -d /home/nobody %u
	</screen>
	<para>You can now join a Microsoft computer to the sports domain (with the root user). After reboot of the Microsoft computer, you will be able to logon with Administrator (password Stargate1), but you will get an error about your roaming profile. We will fix this in the next section.</para>
	<para>When joining the samba domain, you have to enter the credentials of a Linux account that can create users (usually only root can do this). If the Microsoft computer complains with <command>The parameter is incorrect</command>, then you possibly forgot to add the <command>add machine script</command>.</para>
</section>
<section><title>local or roaming profiles</title>
	<para>For your information, if you want to force local profiles instead of roaming profiles, then simply add the following two lines to the global section in smb.conf.</para>
	<screen>
logon home =
logon path =
	</screen>
	<para>Microsoft computers store a lot of User Metadata and application data in a user profile. Making this profile available on the network will enable users to keep their Desktop and Application settings across computers. User profiles on the network are called <command>roaming profiles</command><indexterm><primary>roaming profiles(samba)</primary></indexterm> or <command>roving profiles</command>. The Samba domain controller can manage these profiles. First we need to add the relevant section in smb.conf.</para>
	<screen>
[Profiles]
 comment = User Profiles
 path = /srv/samba/profiles
 readonly = No
 profile acls = Yes
	</screen>
	<para>Besides the share section, we also need to set the location of the profiles share (this can be another Samba server) in the global section.</para>
	<screen>
logon path = \\%L\Profiles\%U
	</screen>
	<para>The <command>&#037;L</command> variable is the name of this Samba server, the <command>&#037;U</command> variable translates to the username. After adding a user to smbpasswd and letting the user log on and off, the profile of the user will look like this.</para>
	<screen>
[root@RHEL4b samba]# ll /srv/samba/profiles/Venus/
total 568
drwxr-xr-x  4 Venus Venus   4096 Jul  5 10:03 Application Data
drwxr-xr-x  2 Venus Venus   4096 Jul  5 10:03 Cookies
drwxr-xr-x  3 Venus Venus   4096 Jul  5 10:03 Desktop
drwxr-xr-x  3 Venus Venus   4096 Jul  5 10:03 Favorites
drwxr-xr-x  4 Venus Venus   4096 Jul  5 10:03 My Documents
drwxr-xr-x  2 Venus Venus   4096 Jul  5 10:03 NetHood
-rwxr--r--  1 Venus Venus 524288 Jul  5  2007 NTUSER.DAT
-rwxr--r--  1 Venus Venus   1024 Jul  5  2007 NTUSER.DAT.LOG
-rw-r--r--  1 Venus Venus    268 Jul  5 10:03 ntuser.ini
drwxr-xr-x  2 Venus Venus   4096 Jul  5 10:03 PrintHood
drwxr-xr-x  2 Venus Venus   4096 Jul  5 10:03 Recent
drwxr-xr-x  2 Venus Venus   4096 Jul  5 10:03 SendTo
drwxr-xr-x  3 Venus Venus   4096 Jul  5 10:03 Start Menu
drwxr-xr-x  2 Venus Venus   4096 Jul  5 10:03 Templates
	</screen>
</section>
<section><title>Groups in NTFS acls</title>
	<para>We have users on Unix, we have groups on Unix that contain those users.</para>
	<screen>
[root@RHEL4b samba]# grep nt /etc/group
...
ntadmins:x:506:Administrator
ntsports:x:507:Venus,Serena,Kim,Figo,Pfaff
nttennis:x:508:Venus,Serena,Kim
ntfootball:x:509:Figo,Pfaff
[root@RHEL4b samba]# 
	</screen>
	<para>We already added Venus to the <command>tdbsam</command> with <command>smbpasswd</command><indexterm><primary>smbpasswd(1)</primary></indexterm>.</para>
	<screen>smbpasswd -a Venus</screen>
	<para>Does this mean that Venus can access the tennis and the sports shares ? Yes, all access works fine on the Samba server. But the nttennis group is not available on the windows machines. To make the groups available on windows (like in the ntfs security tab of files and folders), we have to map unix groups to windows groups. To do this, we use the <command>net groupmap</command><indexterm><primary>net groupmap</primary></indexterm> command.</para>
	<screen>
[root@RHEL4b samba]# net groupmap add ntgroup="tennis" unixgroup=nttennis type=d
No rid or sid specified, choosing algorithmic mapping
Successully added group tennis to the mapping db
[root@RHEL4b samba]# net groupmap add ntgroup="football" unixgroup=ntfootball type=d
No rid or sid specified, choosing algorithmic mapping
Successully added group football to the mapping db
[root@RHEL4b samba]# net groupmap add ntgroup="sports" unixgroup=ntsports type=d
No rid or sid specified, choosing algorithmic mapping
Successully added group sports to the mapping db
[root@RHEL4b samba]# 
	</screen>
	<para>Now you can use the Samba groups on all NTFS volumes on members of the domain.</para>
</section>
<section><title>logon scripts</title>
	<para>Before testing a logon script, make sure it has the proper carriage returns that DOS files have.</para>
	<screen>
[root@RHEL4b netlogon]# cat start.bat 
net use Z: \\DCSPORTS0\SPORTS
[root@RHEL4b netlogon]# unix2dos start.bat 
unix2dos: converting file start.bat to DOS format ...
[root@RHEL4b netlogon]# 
	</screen>
	<para>Then copy the scripts to the netlogon share, and add the following parameter to smb.conf.</para>
	<screen>logon script = start.bat</screen>
</section>
