<section><title>solution : init</title>
        <para>1. Change <command>/etc/inittab</command> so that only two mingetty's are respawned. Kill the other <command>mingetty's</command> and verify that they don't come back.</para>
	<para>Killing the mingetty's will result in init respawning them. You can edit <command>/etc/inittab</command> so it looks like the screenshot below. Don't forget to also run <command>kill -1 1</command>.</para>
	<screen>
[root@RHEL5 ~]# grep tty /etc/inittab 
# Run gettys in standard runlevels
1:2345:respawn:/sbin/mingetty tty1
2:2345:respawn:/sbin/mingetty tty2
3:2:respawn:/sbin/mingetty tty3
4:2:respawn:/sbin/mingetty tty4
5:2:respawn:/sbin/mingetty tty5
6:2:respawn:/sbin/mingetty tty6
[root@RHEL5 ~]# 
	</screen>
        <para>2. Use the Red Hat Enterprise Linux virtual machine. Go to runlevel 5, display the current and previous runlevel, then go back to runlevel 3.</para>
	<screen>
init 5 (watch the console for the change taking place)
runlevel
init 3 (again you can follow this on the console)
	</screen>
        <para>3. Is the sysinit script on your computers setting or changing the PATH environment variable ?</para>
	<para>On Red Hat, grep for PATH in <command>/etc/rc.sysinit</command>, on Debian/Ubuntu check <command>/etc/rc.local</command> and <command>/etc/ini.t/rc.local</command>. The answer is probably no, but on RHEL5 the <command>rc.sysinit</command> script does set the HOSTNAME variable.</para>
	<screen>
[root@RHEL5 etc]# grep HOSTNAME rc.sysinit
	</screen>
	<para>4. List all init.d scripts that are started in runlevel 2.</para>
	<screen>
root@RHEL5 ~# chkconfig --list | grep '2:on'
	</screen>
        <para>5. Write a script that acts like a daemon script in <command>/etc/init.d/</command>. It should have a case statement to act on start/stop/restart and status. Test the script!</para>
	<para>The script could look something like this.</para>
	<screen>
#!/bin/bash
#
# chkconfig: 345 99 01 
# description: pold demo script
#
# /etc/init.d/pold
#

case "$1" in
  start)
     echo -n "Starting pold..."
     sleep 1;
     touch /var/lock/subsys/pold
     echo "done."
     echo pold started >> /var/log/messages
     ;;
  stop)
     echo -n "Stopping pold..."
     sleep 1;
     rm -rf /var/lock/subsys/pold
     echo "done."
     echo pold stopped >> /var/log/messages
     ;;
  *)
     echo "Usage: /etc/init.d/pold {start|stop}"
     exit 1
     ;;
esac
exit 0
	</screen>
	<para>The <command>touch /var/lock/subsys/pold</command> is mandatory and must be the same filename as the script name, if you want the stop sequence (the K01pold link) to be run.</para>
        <para>6. Use <command>chkconfig</command> to setup your script to start in runlevels 3,4 and 5, and to stop in any other runlevel.</para>
	<screen>chkconfig --add pold</screen>
	<para>The command above will only work when the <command># chkconfig:</command> and <command># description:</command> lines in the pold script are there.</para>
	<para></para>
	<para></para>
	<para></para>
</section>
