<?hard-pagebreak?>
<section><title>terminology</title>
	<section><title>repository</title>
		<para>A lot of software and documentation for your Linux distribution is available as <command>packages</command> in one or more centrally distributed <command>repositories</command><indexterm><primary>repository</primary></indexterm>. These <command>packages</command> in such a <command>repository</command> are tested and very easy to install (or remove) with a graphical or command line installer.</para>
	</section>
	<section><title>.deb packages</title>
		<para>Debian, Ubuntu, Mint and all derivatives from Debian and Ubuntu use <command>.deb</command><indexterm><primary>deb(5)</primary></indexterm> packages. To manage software on these systems, you can use <command>aptitude</command><indexterm><primary>aptitude(8)</primary></indexterm> or <command>apt-get</command><indexterm><primary>apt-get(8)</primary></indexterm>, both these tools are a front end for <command>dpkg</command><indexterm><primary>dpkg(8)</primary></indexterm>.</para>
	</section>
	<section><title>.rpm packages</title>
		<para>Red Hat, Fedora, CentOS, OpenSUSE, Mandriva, Red Flag and others use <command>.rpm</command><indexterm><primary>rpm(8)</primary></indexterm> packages. The tools to manage software packages on these systems are <command>yum</command> and <command>rpm</command>.</para>
	</section>
	<section><title>dependency</title>
		<para>Some packages need other packages to function. Tools like <command>apt-get</command>, <command>aptitude</command> and <command>yum</command> will install all <command>dependencies</command> you need. When using <command>dpkg</command> or <command>rpm</command>, or when building from <command>source</command>, you will need to install dependencies yourself.</para>
	</section>
	<section><title>open source</title>
		<para>These repositories contain a lot of independent <command>open source software</command>. Often the source code is customized to integrate better with your distribution. Most distributions also offer this modified source code as a <command>package</command> in one or more <command>source repositories</command>.</para>
		<para>You are free to go to the project website itself (samba.org, apache.org, github.com, ...) an download the <command>vanilla</command><indexterm><primary>vanilla</primary></indexterm> (= without the custom distribution changes) source code.</para>
	</section>
<?hard-pagebreak?>
	<section><title>GUI software management</title>
		<para>End users have several graphical applications available via the desktop (look for 'add/remove software' or something similar).</para>
		<para>Below a screenshot of Ubuntu Software Center running on Ubuntu 12.04. Graphical tools are not discussed in this book.</para>
		<para>
		<mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ubuntu_software_center.png" format="EPS" align="center"></imagedata></imageobject></mediaobject>			
		</para>
	</section>
</section>
