<section><title>terminology</title>
<section><title>router or firewall</title>
	<para>A router is a device that connects two networks. A <command>firewall</command><indexterm><primary>firewall</primary></indexterm> is a device that besides acting as a <command>router</command>, also contains (and implements) rules to determine whether packets are allowed to travel from one network to another. A firewall can be configured to block access based on networks, hosts, protocols and ports. Firewalls can also change the contents of packets while forwarding them.</para>
</section>
<section><title>packet forwarding</title>
	<para>Packet forwarding means allowing packets to go from one network to another. When a multihomed host is connected to two different networks, and it allows packets to travel from one network to another through its two network interfaces, it is said to have enabled <command>packet forwarding</command><indexterm><primary>packet forwarding</primary></indexterm>. </para>
</section>
<section><title>packet filtering</title>
	<para><command>Packet filtering</command><indexterm><primary>packet filtering</primary></indexterm> is very similar to packet forwarding, but every packet is individually tested against rules that decide on allowing or dropping the packet. The rules are stored by iptables.</para>
</section>
<section><title>NAT (network address translation)</title>
	<para>A <command>NAT</command><indexterm><primary>NAT</primary></indexterm> device is a router that is also changing the source and/or target ip-address in packets. It is typically used to connect multiple computers in a private address range (rfc 1918) with the (public) internet. A NAT can hide private addresses from the internet.</para>
</section>
<section><title>PAT (port address translation)</title>
	<para>NAT often includes PAT. A <command>PAT</command><indexterm><primary>PAT</primary></indexterm> device is a router that is also changing the source and/or target tcp/udp port in packets. PAT is Cisco terminology and is used by <command>SNAT</command><indexterm><primary>SNAT</primary></indexterm> (or masquerading) in Linux. RFC 3022 calls it <command>NAPT</command><indexterm><primary>NAPT</primary></indexterm> and defines the NAT/PAT combo as "traditional NAT". A device sold to you as a NAT-device will probably do NAT and PAT.</para>
</section>
<section><title>SNAT (source network address translation)</title>
	<para>In this book we will explain <command>SNAT</command><indexterm><primary>SNAT</primary></indexterm> as "changing the source ip-address when a packet passes our NAT".</para>
</section>
<section><title>masquerading</title>
	<para>In this book we will explain masquerading as "changing the source ip-address when a packet passes our NAT, but only allow connections that originate from our internal network!".</para>
</section>
<section><title>port forwarding</title>
	<para>When static NAT is set up in a way that allows outside connections to enter our private network, then we call it <command>port forwarding</command><indexterm><primary>port forwarding</primary></indexterm>.</para>
</section>
</section>

