	<section><title>Operating Systems History</title>
		<section><title>AT &#038;T Bell Labs</title>
			<para>In 1969 <command>Dennis Ritchie</command> and <command>Ken Thompson</command> wrote <command>UNICS</command> (Uniplexed Information and Computing System) at Bell Labs. Together with <command>Douglas McIlroy</command> they are seen as the creators of Unix. The name Unix is a play on the Multics Operating System for large mainframe computers. Unics (later renamed to Unix) was written for mini computers like the DEC PDP-series. In 1973 they decided to write Unix in C (instead of assembler), to make it portable to other computers. Unix was made available to universities, companies and the US government, including the full source code. This meant that every C programmer could make changes. By 1978 about 600 computers were running Unix. In January 2007 an estimated seventy million websites are running on a Unix-like web server.</para>
		</section>
		<section><title>University of California, Berkeley</title>
			<para>Students of Berkeley were happy to join in the development of Bell Labs Unix, but were not so happy with the restrictive licensing. Unix was open source software, but it still required purchase of a license. So during the eighties, they rewrote all the Unix tools, until they had a complete Unix-like operating system. By 1991, the <command>BSD</command> (Berkeley Software Distribution) branch of Unix was completely separate from the Bell Labs Unix. <command>NetBSD</command>, <command>FreeBSD</command> and <command>OpenBSD</command> are three current Unix-like operating systems derived from the 1991 <command>BSD Net/2</command> codebase. Sun Solaris, Microsoft Windows and Apple MacOSX all use source code from BSD.</para>
		</section>
		<section><title>GNU's not Unix</title>
			<para>Largely because of unhappiness with the restrictive licensing on existing Unix implementations, <command>Richard Stallman</command> initiated the <command>GNU Project</command> in 1983. The GNU project aims to create free software. Development of the GNU operating system started, aiming to create a complete Unix-like branch, seperate from the two other (BSD and Bell Labs).  Today the GNU compiler <command>gcc</command> and most other GNU utilities (like <command>bash</command>) are among the most popular on many Unix-like systems. The official kernel of this project is <command>GNU/Hurd</command>, but you can hardly call that kernel a finished product.</para>
		</section>	
		<section><title>Linux</title>
			<para>Where GNU/Hurd failed, the Linux kernel succeeded! In 1991 a Finnish student named <command>Linus Torvalds</command> started writing his own operating system for his intel 80386 computer. In January 1992, Linus decided to release Linux under the GNU GPL. Thanks to this, thousands of developers are now working on the Linux kernel. Contrary to popular believe, they are not all volunteers. Today big companies like Sun, IBM, Novell, Red Hat, Sony, HP and others are actively paying developers to work on the Linux kernel. Mister Torvalds is still the only one to decide what code gets accepted into the kernel.</para>
		</section>
	</section>
