<?hard-pagebreak?>
<section><title>solution: users</title>
	<para>1. Create the users Serena Williams, Venus Williams and Justine Henin, all of them with password set to stargate, with username (lowercase) as their first name, and their full name in the comment. Verify that the users and their home directory are properly created.</para>
	<screen>useradd -c "Serena Williams" serena ; passwd serena
useradd -c "Venus Williams" venus ; passwd venus
useradd -c "Justine Henin" justine ; passwd justine
tail /etc/passwd ; tail /etc/shadow ; ls /home </screen>
	<screen>Keep user logon names in lowercase!</screen>
	<para>2. Create a user called <command>kornuser</command>, give him the Korn shell (/bin/ksh) as his default shell. Log on with this user (on a command line or in a tty).</para>
	<screen>useradd -s /bin/ksh kornuser ; passwd kornuser</screen>
	<para>3. Create a user named <command>einstime</command> without home directory, give him <command>/bin/date</command> as his default logon shell. What happens when you log on with this user ? Can you think of a useful real world example for changing a user's login shell to an application ?</para>
	<screen>useradd -s /bin/date einstime ; passwd einstime</screen>
	<para>It can be useful when users need to access only one application on the server. Just logging on opens the application for them, and closing the application automatically logs them off.</para>
	<para>4. Try the commands who, whoami, who am i, w, id, echo $USER $UID .</para>
	<screen>who ; whoami ; who am i ; w ; id ; echo $USER $UID</screen>
	<para>5a. Lock the <command>venus</command> user account with usermod.</para>
	<screen>usermod -L venus</screen>
	<para>5b. Use <command>passwd -d</command> to disable the serena password. Verify the serena line in <command>/etc/shadow</command> before and after disabling.</para>
	<screen>grep serena /etc/shadow; passwd -d serena ; grep serena /etc/shadow</screen>
	<para>5c. What is the difference between locking a user account and disabling a user account's password ?</para>
	<para>Locking will prevent the user from logging on to the system with his password (by putting a ! in front of the password in /etc/shadow). Disbling with passwd will erase the password from /etc/shadow.</para>
	<para>6. As <command>root</command> change the password of <command>einstime</command> to stargate.</para>
	<screen>Log on as root and type: passwd einstime</screen>
	<para>7. Now try changing the password of serena to serena as serena.</para>
	<screen>log on as serena, then execute: passwd serena... it should fail!</screen>
	<para>8. Make sure every new user needs to change his password every 10 days.</para>
	<screen>For an existing user: chage -M 10 serena</screen>
	<screen>For all new users: vi /etc/login.defs (and change PASS_MAX_DAYS to 10)</screen>
	<para>9. Set the warning number of days to four for the kornuser.</para>
	<screen>chage -W 4 kornuser</screen>
	<para>10a. Set the password of two separate users to stargate. Look at the encrypted stargate's in /etc/shadow and explain.</para>
	<para>If you used passwd, then the salt will be different for the two encrypted passwords.</para>
	<para>10b. Take a backup as root of /etc/shadow. Use vi to copy an encrypted stargate to another user. Can this other user now log on with stargate as a password ?</para>
	<screen>Yes.</screen>
	<para>11. Put a file in the skeleton directory and check whether it is copied to user's home directory. When is the skeleton directory copied ?</para>
	<screen>When you create a user account with a new home directory.</screen>
	<para>12. Why use vipw instead of vi ? What could be the problem when using vi or vim ?</para>
	<screen>vipw will give a warning when someone else is already using vipw on that file.</screen>
	<para>13. Use chsh to list all shells, and compare to cat /etc/shells. Change your login shell to the Korn shell, log out and back in. Now change back to bash.</para>
	<screen>On Red Hat Enterprise Linux: chsh -l</screen>
	<para>14. Which useradd option allows you to name a home directory ?</para>
	<screen>-d</screen>
	<para>15. How can you see whether the password of user harry is locked or unlocked ? Give a solution with grep and a solution with passwd.</para>
	<screen>grep harry /etc/shadow</screen>
	<screen>passwd -S harry</screen>
</section>
