<section><title>Users</title>
	<section><title>User management</title>
		<para>User management on any Unix can essentially be done in three ways. You can use the <command>graphical</command> tools provided by your distribution. These tools have a look and feel that depends on the distribution. If you are a novice linux user on your home system, then use the graphical tool that is provided by your distribution. This will make sure that you do not run into problems.</para>
		<para>Another option is to use <command>command line tools</command> like useradd, usermod, gpasswd, passwd and others. Server administrators are likely to use these tools, since they are familiar and very similar accross many different distributions. This chapter will focus on these command line tools.</para>
		<para>A third and rather extremist way is to <command>edit the local configuration files</command> directly using vi (or vipw/vigr). Do not attempt this as a novice on production systems!</para>
	</section>
	<section><title>/etc/passwd</title>
		<para>The local user database on Linux (and on most Unixes) is <command>/etc/passwd</command><indexterm><primary>/etc/passwd</primary></indexterm>.</para>
		<screen>
[root@RHEL5 ~]# tail /etc/passwd
inge:x:518:524:art dealer:/home/inge:/bin/ksh
ann:x:519:525:flute player:/home/ann:/bin/bash
frederik:x:520:526:rubius poet:/home/frederik:/bin/bash
steven:x:521:527:roman emperor:/home/steven:/bin/bash
pascale:x:522:528:artist:/home/pascale:/bin/ksh
geert:x:524:530:kernel developer:/home/geert:/bin/bash
wim:x:525:531:master damuti:/home/wim:/bin/bash
sandra:x:526:532:radish stresser:/home/sandra:/bin/bash
annelies:x:527:533:sword fighter:/home/annelies:/bin/bash
laura:x:528:534:art dealer:/home/laura:/bin/ksh
		</screen>
		<para>As you can see, this file contains seven columns seperated by a colon. The columns contain the username, an x, the user id, the primary group id, a description, the name of the home directory and the login shell.</para>
	</section>
	<section><title>root</title>
		<para>The <command>root</command> user also called the <command>superuser</command> is the most powerful account on your Linux system. This user can do almost everything, including the creation of other users. The root user always has userid 0 (regardless of the name of the account).</para>
		<screen>
[root@RHEL5 ~]# head -1 /etc/passwd
root:x:0:0:root:/root:/bin/bash
		</screen>	
	</section>
	<section><title>useradd</title>	
		<para>You can add users with the <command>useradd</command><indexterm><primary>useradd</primary></indexterm> command. 
The example below shows how to add a user named yanina (last parameter), and at the same time forcing the creation of the home directory (-m), setting the name of the home directory (-d) and setting a description (-c). </para>
		<screen>
[root@RHEL5 ~]# useradd -m -d /home/yanina -c "yanina wickmayer" yanina
[root@RHEL5 ~]# tail -1 /etc/passwd
yanina:x:529:529:yanina wickmayer:/home/yanina:/bin/bash
		</screen>
		<para>The user named yanina received userid 529 and <command>primary group</command><indexterm><primary>primary group</primary></indexterm> id 529.</para>
	</section>
	<section><title>/etc/default/useradd</title>	
		<para>Both Red Hat Enterprise Linux and Debian/Ubuntu have a file called <command>/etc/default/useradd</command><indexterm><primary>/etc/default/useradd</primary></indexterm> that contains some default user options. Besides using cat to display this file, you can also use <command>useradd -D</command><indexterm><primary>useradd -D</primary></indexterm>.</para>
		<screen>
[root@RHEL4 ~]# useradd -D
GROUP=100
HOME=/home
INACTIVE=-1
EXPIRE=
SHELL=/bin/bash
SKEL=/etc/skel
		</screen>
	</section>
	<section><title>userdel</title>	
		<para>You can delete the user yanina with <command>userdel</command><indexterm><primary>userdel(1)</primary></indexterm>. The -r option of userdel will also remove the home directory.</para>
		<screen>
[root@RHEL5 ~]# userdel -r yanina
		</screen>
	</section>
	<section><title>usermod</title>
		<para>You can modify the properties of a user with the <command>usermod</command><indexterm><primary>usermod(1)</primary></indexterm> command. This example uses <command>usermod</command> to change the description of the user harry.</para>
		<screen>
[root@RHEL4 ~]# tail -1 /etc/passwd
harry:x:516:520:harry potter:/home/harry:/bin/bash
[root@RHEL4 ~]# usermod -c 'wizard' harry
[root@RHEL4 ~]# tail -1 /etc/passwd
harry:x:516:520:wizard:/home/harry:/bin/bash
		</screen>
	</section>
</section>
